<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A verie godlie and necessary sermon preached before the yong countesse of Cumberland in the North, the 14 of Nouember, 1577. By Christopher Shutt.</title>
            <author>Shutte, Christopher, d. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103003</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3150</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12165)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3150)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1156:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A verie godlie and necessary sermon preached before the yong countesse of Cumberland in the North, the 14 of Nouember, 1577. By Christopher Shutt.</title>
                  <author>Shutte, Christopher, d. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [H. Middleton? for] Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1578]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC; publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A godly sermon preached in the North.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 191) on recto of G4, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3150:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3150:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A verie godlie and neceſſary Sermon, preached before the yong Counteſſe of Comberland in the North, the 24. of Nouember, 1577.</p>
            <p>By Chriſtopher Shutt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Pet. 4.7.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The end of all things is at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, be ye therfore ſober and watch vnto prayer.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 12.13, 14.</bibl>
               <p>Let vs heare the ende of all: feare God, and keepe his Commandements: for this is the whole duetie of man. For God wyll bryng euery woorke vnto iudgement, with euery ſecrete thing, whether it be good or euill.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes Maieſtie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3150:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3150:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the ryght honourable and moſt vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Margaret, Counteſſe of Comberland, C. S. wiſheth all happineſſe and encreaſe of grace, from God the father, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I deſcended (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and my good Ladie) into a ſecret conſideration of the age of this preſent worlde, and of the laſt ende thereof, I perceyued, that our ſauiour Chriſt, in going about by ſundry ſignes and tokens, to foreſhew &amp; premoniſh his elect, of the ruinous decaye and dreadfull downefall of this laſt generation,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.37 Mar. 13.32 Luk. 17.28 1. Pet. 3.20</note> compared the dayes therof to the dayes of Noe before the floode, what time the wicked gaue ouer them ſelues to all vnrighteouſnes, heaping one ſinne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other, vntil the water came and ſwept them all away: to the ende by due remembraunce of Gods fearefull plagues, moſt iuſtly powred vpon that ſinnefull and careleſſe generation, the godly myght in all reuerence and holy conuerſation, watch and wayte within the arke of Chriſtes Churche,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:3"/> for that long wiſhed &amp; moſt welcome time, of their tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation to eternal happines. which thing, whileſt the faithful haue reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, it baniſheth farre from them the vayne delights of earthly vanities, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them moſt readilie to the obedience of the worde of God, whereby they be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned with watchfull Noe, of many future woes &amp; feareful daungers, and alſo enkinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in true godlines and holines of lyfe, with feare &amp; trembling to worke their ſaluation.<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> For ſith they knowe themſelues on earth to be but ſtraungers,<note place="margin">Ebr. 11.13.</note> where al things muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, and haue a ſodaine and a certaine end, their chiefeſt purpoſe ought to be, (as ſayeth the Apoſtle) to be ſober,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.7. 1. theſ. 5.3</note> and to watche in all godly conuerſation vnto prayer. For ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no doubt, the ende ſhall come, as was the comming of the flood in Noe his time, yea euen in an hower, when man thinketh not, and then bleſſed ſhall he be, that is founde in Noe his arke, &amp; watcheth, with his garments cleane,<note place="margin">Apo. 16.15 Mat. 25.10</note> and his lampe of righteouſnes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for he ſhall enter with the bridegrome into reſt, and ſo be ſaued from deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Neither doe I ſee what dayes may be ſo rightly compared with the dayes of Noe, as theſe wherein we lyue: vvherein ſo fewe be
<pb facs="tcp:3150:3"/> righteous, &amp; ſo many ſleeping in ſecuritie of ſinne. Whereat I can not but tremble, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in the ſpirit, the great calamities &amp; end<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les woes which may fal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſinful gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the wickednes wherof is written with a pen of yron, &amp; with the piont of a diamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d:<note place="margin">Ier. 17.1.</note> which theſe eyes of ours are verie likelie to behold,<note place="margin">2 Re. 22.11 Iſa. 49.8. &amp; 55.6.</note> except with good Ioſias we be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in this acceptable time &amp; day of grace, to ſeeke vnto the Lord, &amp; in true repentance, to auoyde his heauie wrath. For, no doubt, ſince the firſt tyme that Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d euer had the knowledge of Gods Goſpel (I ſpeake not of the times of ignoraunce, the myſtie cloudes whereof are paſt) was there in it, neuer more ripenes of all maner of ſinne, and carnall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, then theſe preſent dayes in all eſtates expreſſe, and therefore the more we ſtand in daunger of deſtruction.</p>
            <p>God hath called vs earely and late by the preaching of his worde,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 36 15.</note> but we are nothing better: what remayneth then, but that we feele his ſcourges?<note place="margin">Gen. 19.2. pet. 2.6.</note> When Sodome and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrha woulde not be moued by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of iuſt Lot, what remained but fire and brimſtone from heauen to be their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? When Pharao and the Egyptians refuſed the wordes of Moſes,<note place="margin">Exo. 14.28</note> the red ſea was
<pb facs="tcp:3150:4"/> appointed to be their confuſion.<note place="margin">2. King. 17.6, 14.</note> When Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and Iuda would not be counſelled by the voyce of the prophets of God,<note place="margin">Ier. 4. &amp; 7. &amp; 19.</note> the Aſſyrians and the Babylonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were raiſed vp to plague them &amp; deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. When Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing bettred by all the ſermons &amp; miracles of our ſauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.43</note> and vvould in no vviſe acknovvledge the time of her viſitation, the Romanes vvere appointed to bee her deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. And euen ſo in this ſermon enſuing, it may be gathered, that vvhen the careleſſe man refuſeth to be vvarned by the vvord of god, the Lord hath many plagues prepared for his deſtruction. Can the Lords vvord the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be of ſome ſo ſtubbernely among vs conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and hypocritically of other ſome recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; the fruits of holy life in fevv brought forth, and the land eſcape vnpuniſhed? It is to truely verified of vs, vvhich in times paſt vvas vvitneſſed of the dayes of Noe, vvherin al fleſh had corrupted it ſelfe, &amp; filled the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vvith iniquitie, whileſt only Noe and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie being but a fewe in number, vvere oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in making of the Arke for their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Wherof (Madame) vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before your honour, more compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly perhaps, through ſhortnes of the time,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:4"/> then eyther your Honour could haue deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or I my ſelfe haue vviſhed, I was then of ſome ſo vehemently required, to impart in vvriting to their further conſolation, vvhat then in pulpit I had ſpoken, that notvvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I iudged my labours to ſimple to paſſe abroad, and my ſelfe farre vnmeete for ſuch a purpoſe: yet durſt I not deny to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort ſuch, as thirſted after ſpiritual knovvledge, &amp; to warne ſuch as would eſcape, of the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to come, and ſo eftſoones reſolued my ſelf, as nere as god vvould giue me leaue to explane and augment, vvhat my purpoſe vvas then in the pulpit to vtter. Neither had I far to ſeeke to vvhoſe patronage, I might commend vvhat herein I vvent about, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as dayly your honours godlie zeale and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous life, called me to offer it vnto your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: whoſe vvilling hart, not onely I haue had experience of, to accept my laboures in good part before this time, but alſo ſee your vvhole endeuour alvvayes bent to further the proceedings of the Goſpell, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame this ignorant country fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their vvon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted erroures, to the church &amp; arke of Chriſt. A rare vertue in your ſexe, and ſuch as may conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the ſlackenes of ſome other kinds, vvho care full litle hovve it goeth vvith
<pb facs="tcp:3150:5"/> the Churche, ſo they them ſelues may liue at vvill and eaſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.30.</note> But as your honour hath choſen the vvay of trueth to bee your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.30.</note> and eke your perfect wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and nobilitie,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.6.</note> and alſo by your happy and welcome comming into theſe rude and deſert partes, haue miniſtred great ſolace to the godlie: ſo do I wiſhe with all my heart, and dayly pray, that your honour may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily proceed, as you haue vertuouſly begun, to the great benefitte of Chriſtes church, &amp; to the comfort of your quiet conſcience in the laſt day.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours moſt humble in Christ, Christopher Shutt.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer type="tailpiece">
               <figure>
                  <head>C B</head>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3150:5"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A verie godlie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Sermon preached before the</hi> young Counteſſe of Comberlande in the North, the 24. of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. 1577. by <hi>M. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Shutt.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ebr.</hi> 11.7.</bibl>
                  <p>By faith Noe being warned of God,<note place="margin">The Theame.</note> of the things which were as yet not ſeene, moued with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, prepared the arke, to the ſauing of his houſholde, through the which arke, he condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the world, and was made heire of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, which is by faith.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy ghoſt (right honourable and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued) layeth forth to our conſideration,<note place="margin">Ebr. 11. toto.</note> in this chapter, a long rehearſal of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful men of God, in the former ages of the worlde, whoſe perfect faith and true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made manifeſt, to all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in this place of ſcripture: who after that by faith they were iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before God,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.2 &amp; 4.5, 6. Iſai. 6.3.</note> like trees of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:6"/> they brought forth the fruites of al obedience, in godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. Among whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle reckoneth vp the liuely faith and godly life of righteous Noe, in the latter end of the firſt age.<note place="margin">Ge. 6. toto.</note> Who beholding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great ripenes of ſinne, and corruption of all fleſh,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.20 &amp; 2. pet. 2.5.</note> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowing waters to be puniſhed, being warned of God, with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and feare, prepared the arke, for the ſafetie of him ſelfe and his houſhold, and alſo to condemne the great ſecuritie of that careleſſe generation:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.38</note> whereby hee obtained through the free mercy of God, to be called the heire of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which is according vnto faith. The due remembrance whereof, may enkindle in vs, if we lothe not our ſaluation, the vigilant care wherewith we ought to be preſſed, in this laſt age and winding vp of theſe our ſorowful dayes, wherein
<pb facs="tcp:3150:6"/> ſuch ripenes of al iniquities, ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible contempt of Gods word, and ſo manifeſt vngodlines, foretel and prognoſticate the ſmall fall of this totering world, to be very neere an end, that when the ſame ſhal come, we might be ſaued within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> arke of Chriſtes Church with faithfull Noe, rather then by our carnall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, to hazard loſſe of bodie and ſoule for euer.</p>
            <p>The wordes of the Apoſtle as they lye in order, containe eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, two things to be obſerued. The one, whereupon it came, that Noe was moued to prepare the arke: The other, what effect y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> arke had, when it was made. The former is contayned in theſe words, <hi>By faith Noe being warned of God, of the things which were as yet not ſeene, moued with reuerence, prepared the arke.</hi> Wherein is perceiued, firſt an admonition to be giuen him: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:7"/> a readines in him to beleue the ſame: and laſt of all the making of the arke, to declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obedience of his faith. The other followeth in the text: <hi>He prepared it, to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his houſhold, through which arke, he condemned the world, and was made heire of the righteouſnes, which is by faith.</hi> Wherein is noted, what effect it had in Noe and his familie: next of al, what effect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the wicked: &amp; laſtly, howe this obedience of Noe, was accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and rewarded of God.</p>
            <p>Albeit (right honourable and beloued) the electe of God in this life, walke through the valleye of teares and ſhadows of death,<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.4.</note> yet the Lord continueth, their light &amp; ſtrength and rocke of ſure defence,<note place="margin">Pſa. 27.1, 5.</note> who in the time of trouble, will hide them in his tabernacle, that not one heare of their head ſhal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe:<note place="margin">Luk. 21.18</note> but when the floodes of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities
<pb facs="tcp:3150:7"/> approch, he giueth them warning to eſcape, and ſo deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them out of temptation,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.9.</note> and reſerueth the vniuſt vnto the day of iudgement to bee puniſhed. Which warning the Lorde gaue now to Noe, with whom he had,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 6.8.14.</note> according to the riches of his grace, entred into a couenant, to the end he might prepare an arke for his deliueraunce, againſt the comming of the flood, wherewith the wicked ſhoulde bee drowned. In like maner when the ſinnes of the Sodomites cryed for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance from heauen,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.15</note> the Lorde premoniſhed righteous Lot, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wearied with their vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to ſeparate him ſelfe and his from them, leaſt he ſhoulde haue periſhed in the flame of the citie, which was readie with fire and brimſtone to be deſtroyed.<note place="margin">Nom. 16. toto.</note> When Corah, Dathan, and Abiron,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> with their companie, had repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ordinaunce of God, and contrary to his commandement, offred vp ſtraunge incenſe, and ſo prouoked the wrath of the Lorde againſt them, the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Moſes &amp; Aaron to exempt them ſelues &amp; the reſt of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation from their companie, leſt they ſhould haue bin ſwalow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp together with them, quicke into hell. Such faythfull war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſpirite of God, giueth to the elected ſaintes in the reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they ſhould come out of Babylon and touche no vncleane thing,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.4</note> leaſt in being partakers of hir ſinnes, they ſhould haue bin partakers of hir plagues. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee may learne the great care,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.15 &amp; 121.4.</note> which the Lorde hath for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his people, forewarning them alwayes of the dangers to come, to the ende they might ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:3150:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> reſt vnder his protection. For ſurely he will do nothing,<note place="margin">Amos. 3.7</note> but he firſt reuealeth his word vnto his Prophets, that they may warne his choſen earely and late,<note place="margin">Iere. 7.13.</note> to ſaue them ſelues in time of trouble. The Lord foretolde the people of Iſrael &amp; of Iuda,<note place="margin">Iſa. 10.5. Iere. 25.9.</note> by the mouth of his Prophetes, their captiuitie in Aſſyria &amp; Babylon, long time before they felt any ſore, that the godly might ſeeke deliueraunce. Our Sauiour Chriſt premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his elect of many daungers to come,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.16</note> that thoſe which were in Iurie, might flee vnto the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and ſeeke to ſaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, vnder the croſſe.<note place="margin">Act. 20.29. 2. theſ. 2.3 1. tim. 4.1. 2. tim. 3.1.</note> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles foreſhewed the comming of falſe prophetes, and of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt the man of ſinne, and of his manifolde abominations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he ſhould poyſon the world, that the godly might bee the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:3150:9"/> furniſhed with the woorde of trueth, to preſerue them ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his wily traines, of mans decrees and vaine inuentions. We haue bene admoniſhed theſe nineteene yeeres and more, and warned by the preaching of the Goſpell, to forſake papiſtrie and ſuperſtition, to leaue our ſinfull wayes, and to folowe the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of life, that we might be ſaued from deſtruction. We haue bin at our wits ende,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.25.</note> with ſignes and ſtrange reports, and fearfull ſights from heauen, calling vs to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance. We haue felt of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumptions,<note place="margin">Deut. 28. Amos. 4.</note> &amp; diuers kindes of death, with loſſe of friends and other things, to humble vs to flie from the wrath to come. We haue bene aſtonied with the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ruine of Monarchies &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes rounde about vs, that we ſleepe not in ſecuritie. And dayly
<pb facs="tcp:3150:9"/> we doe ſee ſuch troubles euerye where, as do forewarne our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, if in time we doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Wherfore as the Lord hath ſet watchmen ouer vs in bidding vs take heede to the ſounde of the trumpet,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.17 &amp; 33.4.</note> let vs beware with reuerence and feare: for if wee walke after the ſtubbernes of our ſtonie heartes, and ſaye with the wicked, wee will not take heede,<note place="margin">Iere. 6.17, 19. Iere. 5 25.</note> then will hee bring vpon vs the fruites of our owne imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all the curſes of the law, and ſo we ſhall lye downe in our owne confuſion, and bee couered with our ſhame, becauſe wee loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed inſtruction,<note place="margin">Prou. 1.29.</note> and hated to bee reformed. For ſurely the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the wicked ſleepeth not, though yet they liue in al proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.7. pſal. 37.35. iere. 12.1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and floriſh as a greene Bay tree. Let not vs then folowe their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſion of ryote,<note place="margin">1. Pet 4.4</note> but in time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb facs="tcp:3150:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Lordes warning with Noe,<note place="margin">Micah. 6.8.</note> to hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble our ſelues to walke before our God. The Storcke in the ayre (as ſayth the Prophete) knoweth her appointed times,<note place="margin">Iere. 8.7.</note> the Turtle, the Crane, and the Swallowe, obſerue their oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of comming, and ſhall not we knowe the iudgements of our God?<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.3.</note> Or can the Oxe know his maſters ſtall,<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.3.</note> or the Aſſe his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters cribbe, and ſhall not Iſrael know his God? Let vs be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the voyce of God, let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue inſtruction and be wiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time.<note place="margin">Prou. 8.33.</note> For bleſſed is the man, that heareth wiſdome, watching day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at hir gates, and giuing atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance at the poſtes of hir doores: For hee that findeth hir, findeth life, and ſhall obtaine the fauour of the Lord, and onely this is our wiſdome and perfect vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to receiue and obſerue the
<pb facs="tcp:3150:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> admonitions of our God.</p>
            <p>When Noe were thus admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the Lorde, he did not by and by forget his worde, or choke it with the cares of life,<note place="margin">Luk. 8.14.</note> and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſſe of liuing, then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing: but as his fayth was wrought thereby, ſo was he now emboldned and his fayth encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and preſerued by theſe admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.12. Rom. 10, 17. 2. Theſ. 3.3</note> concerning thinges to come. For as by meats &amp; drinks the bodie is increaſed, and by the wholſome counſell of phyſitions, the ſicknes to be feared, is preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: ſo by the woorde of God, the fayth of Noe was increaſed, and by the admonitions thereof, the daungers to bee feared were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded, whileſt he willingly gaue credit to that which was ſpoken. By this his readineſſe to beleeue the worde, appeareth plainly (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) the faythfull heart, which
<pb facs="tcp:3150:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> the godly ought to haue towards the ſame, that in beleeuing the worde of trueth,<note place="margin">Leui. 26.3, 12. ier. 7.23 Nu. 10.29</note> the Lord may be their God, and they his people. This readineſſe was in the Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, when they left their owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, to go with the Iſraelites into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land of Canaan, that they might be further inſtructed in the law of God.<note place="margin">2. Kin. 22.21, 13.</note> This readines was in the good king Ioſias, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his heart melted within him for feare of the plagues of God towardes the land, neither ceaſſed he, vntill he had enquired of the Lord what was to be done.<note place="margin">Pſal. 84, 6.</note> This readineſſe was in all thoſe which wente through the valley of teares, from ſtrength to ſtrength, to ſeeke the Lorde in Sion. This readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was in the Prophetes and Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Mat. 19, 27</note> whileſt they left all thinges to obey the will of God.<note place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> This readines was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:3150:11"/> when they were fired with the wordes of Peter, and with peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hearts required what to do. And this ought to be our readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes towards the word of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and towards the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of the moſt higheſt, that whileſt he ſpeaketh, we giue eare,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.24. ier. 7.26, 27</note> whileſt he crieth, that wee make anſwere, and whileſt it is ſaid, to day,<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.7, 8</note> that we beleue and heare his voyce. Theſe ſhould be the daies, wherein men ſhoulde follow no more the ſtubbornneſſe of theyr wicked hearts,<note place="margin">Iere. 3.17.</note>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 4.1, 2. pſal. 122.1.</note> but rather ſhould goe vp to the mountaine of the lord, to be inſtructed in his lawes with reuerence and feare.<note place="margin">Eſai. 2.18.20.</note> Theſe ſhould be the dayes, wherein the idoles ſhoulde de deſtroyed, and men ſhoulde forſake their molten gods.<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.3</note> Theſe ſhould be the ſweete and ioyfull dayes of Ieruſalem, wherein the people ſhoulde offer
<pb facs="tcp:3150:12"/> willing offrings of obedience and thankfulneſſe. Theſe ſhoulde be the <hi>Halcionios dies</hi> of the Church, when righteouſneſſe and peace, when mercie and trueth ſhoulde meete and kiſſe eche other.<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> But in ſteade of readines to the worlde, the eares of many are vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed,<note place="margin">Iere. 6.10.</note> that they neither can, nor will heare the lawe of God. In ſtead of caſting away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vanities of Idoles,<note place="margin">Apo. 13.8, 16.</note> they are marked with the beaſtes marke, whome they worſhip. In ſtead of quietnes &amp; loue, the heartes of many are ſet on miſchiefe, whileſt diſcorde, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie and debate preuaile ſo much.<note place="margin">Colo. 3.8.</note> I feare therefore, theſe dayes are more like the daies of Noe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of trueth bare rule amongſt ſo many.<note place="margin">Gene. 6.</note> They are the dayes of the prouocation in the wildernes,<note place="margin">Nu. 11.4, 5. pſal. 95.9.</note> wherein the delights of Egyptiacal ſeruitude, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb facs="tcp:3150:12"/> before the ſweete <hi>Manna</hi> of euerlaſting happines. I wonder what euill ſpirite hath bewitched men,<note place="margin">Galat. 3.1.</note> that they ſhould not beleeue the truth. Why haue they put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them an whoriſh face,<note place="margin">Iere. 3.3.</note> and a ſhameles looke, and made their hearts like an adamant,<note place="margin">Zach. 7.12.</note> whileſt they walke in the errour of theyr hearts, and in the vanitie of their own imaginations? Euery man flattereth himſelfe in his owne wayes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 65.5.</note> &amp; thinketh him ſelfe more holy then his fellowe, but yet hee pluckes not the beame of pride out of his eie.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.3, 4.5.</note> Wee ſay with fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Iuda,<note place="margin">Iere. 2.23.</note> that we be not pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor haue folowed after Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim: and yet we are vncleane, by meanes of popiſhe ſuperſtition.<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.4</note> Wee bragge and boaſt with the proud Phariſie,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.11. Pſal. 38.4.</note> of our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: yet feele we not the burthen of our ſinnes and faith in Chriſt, and therfore remaine vniuſtified.
<pb facs="tcp:3150:13"/> We ſay with the angell of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 3.17 18.</note> that we be rich and much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed with goodes, and haue neede of nothing: &amp; yet we know not that we are wretched, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, poore and blind &amp; naked. What remayneth then for vs, but to bye of the Lords fine gold, that we may be rich, &amp; white rayment, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be clothed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our filthie nakednes do not appeare, &amp; that our eies may be anointed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the eie ſalue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may ſee, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to obey the truth, &amp; to be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Noe, to make preparation againſt the flouds of euil to come.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially (welbeloued) the faith of Noe appeared in this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaw the things to come, which preſently could not by outwarde ſenſes be diſcerned. For, ſeeing that the floud was not come, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an hundreth and twentie yeeres were ended, the tract of time might haue remoued and
<pb facs="tcp:3150:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> baniſhed away the remembrance thereof. It might alſo haue ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med incredible to fleſh and bloud, that ſuch a water ſhould come ſo quickly: beſides all theſe, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked folowed their delights with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect: and to be ſhort, theſe threatnings of ſuch floods might haue bene iudged vaine: but Noe his faith did mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aloft, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched aboue the capacitie of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſenſes, and looked vp to things more excellent by much, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could by outward meanes be vnderſtood: which things yet hid and not apparant, the holy ghoſt ſealeth in our harts, for our more aſſurance.<note place="margin">Ebr. 11.1.</note> According whereunto the Apoſtle calleth fayth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of things hoped for, &amp; the ſure demonſtration of thinges which are not ſeene: thereby not onely lifting vp our fayth to things to come, but alſo fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring vs of the performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:14"/> for God is faithful which hath promiſed.<note place="margin">Ebr. 10.23.</note> We are alreadie ſaued by hope,<note place="margin">Ro. 8.24, 25</note> but hope that is ſeene is no hope: for how can a man hope for that which he ſeeth? but if we hope for that which wee ſee not, we doo with pacience abide for it.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.7.</note> And this treaſure wee haue in our earthen veſſels, that the excellencie of that power might be of God, &amp; not of vs. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from whence we looke for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> euen Ieſus Chriſt, with whom our life is hid in God,<note place="margin">Col. 3.3, 4.</note> that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, which is our life, ſhal appeare, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we alſo appeare with him in glorie: Such a ſure perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things to come had Noe, neither wauered he in fayth at all. This is that exceeding comfort, which maketh glad the hearts of the elect in the middeſt of the ſorowes of this life, aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beholding with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eies of faith,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:14"/> ſuch thinges as neither the eie of man hath ſeene,<note place="margin">Eſai. 64.4. 1. cor. 2.9.</note> nor his eare hath heard, nor yet his heart percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or vnderſtoode. Such an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted hope and truſt had the godly fathers vnder and before the lawe,<note place="margin">Gene. 3.15 &amp; 15.5. &amp; 22.17, 18. Deu. 18.18 2. Sa. 7, 16.</note> when with the eyes of fayth they behelde the Meſſias &amp; ſauiour Chriſt to come, and ſo were iuſtified, as we beleue now, that he is come alreadie, and hath wrought our redemption. Such was the faith of Abraham, Iſaac and Iacob,<note place="margin">Ebr. 11.13.</note> concerning the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the land of Canaan, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they were but ſtrangers vpon the earth, &amp; had not a foot bredth to poſſeſſe, beleeuing what the Lord had promiſed, ſhould ſurely come to paſſe. Such an aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of fayth had Moſes, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the delightes of Egypt, and the pleaſures of Pharaos court,<note place="margin">Ebr. 11.24, 25, 26.</note> to ſuffer perſecution with his
<pb facs="tcp:3150:15"/> brethren, looking to the promiſed rewarde. This aſſured fayth of thinges to come had good king Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.28, 29.</note> when he truſted that his throne ſhoulde continue, and be eſtabliſhed for euer. This aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of things to come, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt commended to his diſciples, againſt the aſſaults of perſecution, promiſing them, that they ſhuld ſit vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> twelue thrones with him,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.28. luk. 22.30.</note> and iudge the twelue tribes of Iſrael. This aſſurance had the Apoſtle Paul, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to attaine the righteouſnes of fayth,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.8, 9 10. 2. Ti. 4.8.</note> and reſurrection of the iuſt, that he might weare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown which God had layde vp in ſtore for him. And what els moued the ſaints of God,<note place="margin">Apo. 12.11</note> to withſtande the beaſt, and not to loue their liues to death, but that by fayth they ſawe the newe Ieruſalem? And this is that golden ſaying of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3150:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> going to be martyred,<note place="margin">Euſe. lib. 3. cap. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Nihil moror viſibilium, nec inuiſibilium, modo Ieſum Chriſtum acquiram.</hi> I neither (ſayeth he) care for things nowe ſeene, nor thinges which are not ſeene, ſo that I may laye holde of Ieſus Chriſt. This is our comfort (dearely beloued) in theſe daungerous dayes and byl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of the world, that our faith is not fixed of things preſent, but of thinges to come. For though now we be the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God (as ſayeth the Apoſtle) yet doth it not appeare what we ſhalbe.<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.2.</note> For we know, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſhal appeare, wee ſhall bee like to him, for wee ſhall ſee him as he is. We ſee now in a glaſſe darkly, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we ſee him face to face:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> we know but nowe in part, but then ſhall wee knowe, euen as we are knowne. We are now corruptible,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.53.</note> but we ſhal be clothed with incorruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:3150:16"/> We are now but mortal, but this mortall ſhall be ſwalowed vp of immortalitie. We are now afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; in diſtres,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17, 18.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame is but for a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; yet cauſeth in vs, a moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; eternal weight of glory, while we looke not on the things which are ſeen, but on the things which are not ſeene: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things which are ſeen, are but te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things which are not ſeene,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23, 24, 25.</note> are eternall. Though for a while we feele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reliques of ſin in vs prouoking vs to euil, yet looke we dayly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time ſhal come, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this body of ſin may be don away We feele in our ſelues the ſparks and ſeed of much vnrighteouſnes, yet do we hope in ſtead therof, we ſhalbe clothed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fine reynes and righteouſnes of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Apo. 19.8. 1. Cor. 1.30 2. cor. 5, 21. Pſal. 32.1, 2</note> and all our tranſgreſſions to be pardoned. We feele for a litle, hunger &amp; colde, yet do we hope for the abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of all delightes &amp; heauenly treaſures.
<pb facs="tcp:3150:16"/> We daily ſorowe and weepe,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.8, 9, 10. 2. pet. 2.7.</note> &amp; are vexed with the vncleane conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wicked, yet truſt we that our ſorowe ſhalbe turned into ioy,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.20, 21. Apoc. 21.4</note> &amp; all teares wyped from our eyes. We now abyde with patience the tauntes and checkes of Antichriſt and his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers,<note place="margin">Apo. 14.9.</note> but yet we ſee by faith, that Babylon the mother of all abominations,<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.4</note> ſhal ſodainly fall and come to nought, for that her ſinnes are in remembrance with God.<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.5</note> We dayly feare the aſſaultes of ſinne &amp; death, yet do we knowe by faith that Chriſt hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered them for vs.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21 coloſ. 2.14. apo. 20.14.</note> We feele our frailtie in this lyfe, and thraldome to infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.31, 32.</note> yet do we hope for euerlaſting reſt in the reſurrection of the iuſt. Such is the aſſurance of our faith, ſurmounting farre the reache of mannes capacitie: ſhee wauereth not, ſhe ſincketh not, ſhee doubteth not (as ſaith the miſbeleeuing pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> leaning to his ydle woorkes) but ſhe maketh the good conſcience ſure,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.16.19. &amp; 8.16, 38, 39. Ebr. 10.22</note> and alwayes hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whileſt ſhee plainly beholdeth the things as yet not ſeene, but ſurelie for to come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>Further, whereas this readines of Noe was ioyned with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, it is (dearely beloued) to teache vs, that his faith was directed both to the promiſſe of the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was receyued into fauour, &amp; alſo to the threatnings of GOD, whereby the Lord menaced the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued to come, and ſo did tremble. And as by the former, he was aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of gods fauour, ſo by the other, in reſpect of his own infirmitie, he feared leaſt he ſhould haue periſhed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked. Wherein we muſt note two things, the one, what is the obiect of our faith: the other, how it trembleth in reſpect of our
<pb facs="tcp:3150:17"/> ſelues, at the plagues denounced,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.5, 11. Rom. 8.38</note> &amp; yet for all that, is aſſured of Gods mercie.</p>
            <p>Our faith is leueled &amp; directed, eſpecially at Chriſt the obiect ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For like as the Iſraelites did w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their bodily eyes behold the braſen ſerpent, &amp; were cured:<note place="margin">Num. 21.9. Ioh. 3.14.</note> euen ſo doth fayth the eye of our ſoule, beholde the Sonne of God lift vp vpon the altar of the croſſe for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And like as wholeſome meates onely nouriſh the body, euen ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dooth feede our faith, but Chriſt crucified, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread of lyfe:<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.48.51.</note> at whoſe worke of redemption, our faith muſt alwaies looke, or els we muſt needes be preſſed down, with the terrour of our owne conſcience into hell.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.28 Ioh. 3.16. Col. 1.19. and 2.3.</note> For ſeeing that the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Goſpell are a readie way to leade vs to the knowledge of Gods mercy reueyled in Chriſt, in whom it pleaſeth the father that al
<pb facs="tcp:3150:18"/> fulnes ſhould dwell, and in whom are all the treaſures of wiſedome &amp; vnderſtanding, to whom wee can not come, but being fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that our ſaluation reſteth in his free grace and mercy: the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte of our faith, which ſhee doth chiefly behold, muſt of neceſſitie be the promiſes of the Goſpel, laying forth to vs Chriſte crucified for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. &amp; 5. &amp; 6. tot. Ro. 5.19.</note> by whoſe obedience our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is wrought, &amp; in whom alone the Father is well pleaſed:<note place="margin">Mat. 3.17.</note> for in him our faith beholdeth the law of God fulfilled for vs, who tooke the curſe thereof vpon him ſelf,<note place="margin">Galat. 3.13 Ephe. 1.7. &amp; 2.13.</note> that he might make vs bleſſed. In his blood our faith beholdeth perfect redemption and remiſſion of our ſinnes: &amp; we which were farre of, are now made neere, &amp; reconciled to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24</note> By his ſtripes, we feele by faith, that we are made whole, &amp; clothed with his righteouſnes:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.30</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3150:18"/> by his onely ſacrifice done once for euer,<note place="margin">Ebre. 9.12. &amp; 10.10, 18</note> our faith beholdeth eternall redemption purchaſed, and them conſecrat for euer, that are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: ſo that where forgiueneſſe of ſinnes is, there is no more obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſinne. In him, through him,<note place="margin">Ro. 5.1. &amp; 8.34. Ephe. 3.12</note> and for his ſake, faith boldly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to the throne of grace, to find mercy to helpe in time of need:<note place="margin">Ebr. 4.16.</note> for he is our peace, our aduocate and the propitiation for our ſinnes.<note place="margin">1. Iohn 2.2</note> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, by faith in him wee are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Gods fauour,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16. Ro. 8.1, 34.</note> and of eternal lyfe, ſo that there is nowe no dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to ſuch as bee graffed in Chriſte Ieſu, which walke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſpirit, &amp; not according to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fleſhe. For it is Chriſt that doth iuſtifie vs, and therefore none can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne vs, none ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay any thing to our charge, neyther ſeparate vs from the loue of God. And thus is Chriſt with his death and paſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:19"/> the onely obiect of our faith. Alſo theſe two, Chriſt crucified, and our faith, alwayes muſt goe together. For, as the ſunne ſhining in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, auaileth him not, that hath none eyes to ſee the ſame, neyther him that wincketh with his eyes &amp; will not ſee, but only him that doth behold the light thereof: So doeth the death of Chriſte profit him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which lacketh true faith to lay holde vpon the ſame,<note place="margin">Galat 2.20 Ioh. 3. &amp; 6. tot.</note> but onely ſuch as by a liuely &amp; fruitfull faith, applie the ſame vnto them ſelues.</p>
            <p>Beſides that Noe his faith was ſpecially directed to the promiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenant, yet was he made more watchful a great deale, and kept in obedience, by the terrours of the flood, and ſo with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling wrought his ſaluation,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wauered in the faith, but that he feared in tranſgreſſing to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the wicked. For this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb facs="tcp:3150:19"/> the plagues powred vpon the wicked, bring forth in the liues and conuerſation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly, that theſe are made more circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpect by much to ſtande in feare, leaſt they ſhould fall.<note place="margin">Deut. 29.2 &amp; 18.12.</note> When Moſes counſelled the Iſraelites to the obſeruance of the law, hee warned them to feare, by the plagues powred vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and vpon the Canaanites, thereby to keepe them in obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. When Ieremie threatned captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto the land of Iuda, hee vſed the captiuitie of the ten tribes then being in Aſſyria,<note place="margin">Iere. 3.8.</note> to make them tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; afrayed. When the Apoſtle vnderſtood the hautines of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines,<note place="margin">Ro. 11.18.</note> he vſed the puniſhment of the Iewes,<note place="margin">1. Co. 10.5</note> in whoſe place they were graffed, to bridle them and keepe them in obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. When the Corinthians waxed proude of the graces of God, the Apoſtle layed forth the plagues of God agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:3150:20"/> the Iewes in the wildernes, that who ſo ſtood, might take heede hee did not fal. And this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe why the holy Ghoſt calleth vs to feare, that we ſhould not by our diſſolute life ſhake of and loſe our faith, and make the laſt end worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.<note place="margin">Luk. 11.26 Mala. 1.6.</note> The ſonne honoureth his father, and a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his maſter. If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God be a father to vs, we muſt honour him, if he be a Lorde, wee muſt feare his ſtripes. O that we had the reuerent dread and feare which Noe had, it would make vs readie to know and doo the will of God, it would bring forth an vnfai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned loathing and hatred of ſinne in vs, it would budde forth the ſtudie of true godlines, it would ſet vs forwarde to the loue of God &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt of our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But though we feel the ſcourge of God ſo ſore, that there is no whole part alreadie in the body,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.6.</note> yet are we not humbled
<pb facs="tcp:3150:20"/> nor afraid: though we be ſtrike<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Iere. 5.3.</note> we do not ſorowe: though we be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, we refuſe to receyue correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For why? we haue made our faces harder then a ſtone, and will not returne though we be warned of the future woes. In ſteade of keeping the commandementes of GOD,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.9.</note> we obſerue the precepts of men, wherewith we worſhip God in vaine. In ſteade of feare &amp; true obedience,<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1, 2, 3.</note> we looſe the bridle to the effuſion of al ryot. In ſteade of true religion, nothing is to be found but either meere Atheiſme,<note place="margin">Apo. 3.16.</note> or flat diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation. In ſteade of holines of life, we deck our ſelues with pride, and in ſteade of iudgement &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.7. Hoſ. 4.2.</note> we bring forth oppreſſion and crying of the poore, and bloud toucheth bloud. Where is now the reuerence and feare, wherein wee liue, or howe are we reſtrained fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offending, by the remembrance of
<pb facs="tcp:3150:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſea of euils to come? No, no (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) we feare men more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god. And if in ſome things we ſubmitte our obedience, to the hearing of the ſcriptures, and ordinarie admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Sacraments in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall aſſemblies, yet is ſuch duetie in many of vs but conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and not of a good and zealous heart, delighting in the Goſpell. But if we do neglect, we feare the magiſtrates ſword. Wel, let vs not play to long with our fleeing ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.13.</note> but ſanctifie the Lorde, that he may be our feare, and betime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne with Noe to feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſt: for if the wrath of God be kindled but a litle,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.12.</note> bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him. And thus ye ſee, that our faith is ſpecially direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the promiſes of God, and yet muſt we not be careles and voyde of feare, and ſo do what we liſt, but alwayes we muſt ſtand in awe, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3150:21"/> be afrayde to offende, leſt with the wicked we haue reward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He prepared the Arke.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Noe was in ſundrie wiſe thus mooued, he addreſſed himſelf without delay to the making of the Arke, thereby to witnes his obedience of fayth. For euen as water floweth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fountaine, ſo doth this his obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſpring from faith, whereby he had apprehended the promiſe of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. His obedience appeareth the more, for that the making of this work was tedious, and often hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furiouſnes of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: which vnneth hee could pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently haue abiden, if that hee had not ſafely reſted in the promiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenant. But faith the miſtres of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, brought forth ſuch fruits as might expreſſe his willing mind, to obey the Lords commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. This is that excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che of our religion, that our faith be not fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:22"/> as our aduerſaries make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.16, 17. &amp; 12.33</note> but like a good tree it muſt bring forth the fruites of integritie and righteouſnes of life. For euen as fyre burneth &amp; cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out heate, no more then the ſunne without his light:<note place="margin">Iam. 2.14. Ro. 12.1, 2. Ephe. 2.10</note> euen ſo is it impoſſible for a true faith, to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good workes. which although they do not iuſtifie vs before God, yet are they to bee done, that our obedience of faith may thereby be diſcerned,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16. Rom. 1.5.</note> which may bee ſeene, whileſt wee walke in the lawe of God.</p>
            <p>When Moſes was ready to take his leaue of the Iſraelites, howe earneſtly he required of them obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the law of god,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.6. &amp; 28. toto.</note> it is moſt manyfeſt throughout the whole booke of Deutero. When Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el had appointed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iewes a king,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.14.</note> how ſweetely doth hee moue them to the obedience of the law? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:3150:22"/> Dauid would publiſh and ſing the praiſes of God, how vehementlye doth he cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel the Iewes to heare the voyce of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.7, 8. &amp; 119. toto.</note> and not to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den their hearts, as in the deſerte? When the Prophets would haue the people to turne to the Lorde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his wrath might bee turned from them, their chief perſuaſion reſteth herin, that they would teſtify their faith, not by the multitude of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,<note place="margin">Ier. 7.22, 23 Hoſ. 6.6. Micah. 6.8.</note> but by obeying the worde of God. This obedience our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt requireth of his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, if they loue him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.15.</note> to keepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements: &amp; this is the ſame which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle Paul calleth the obedience of faith:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.5.</note> to the end af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we bee iuſtified, wee might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the ſame by our obedience to the law of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 6. toto. &amp; 8.1. &amp; 12.1. Gal. 5.1. Epheſ. 4.1. &amp;c.</note> and therefore in al his epiſtles, after the treatiſe of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth the fruits of newnes of life. whereby (dearly
<pb facs="tcp:3150:23"/> beloued) wee are to learne, how fruitfull our obedience ought to be in good workes,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.14. 1. pet. 2.12</note> for ſo much as our faith is made manifeſt therby, god is glorified,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.8. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us 2.14 &amp; 3.14.</note> and our brethren profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hee hath made vs a peculiar people vnto him ſelf, that we ſhuld be folowers of good workes, wee muſt therefore liue holily, ſoberly, &amp; righteouſly in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t world. he hath redeemed vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hands of our enemies,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.71, 74.</note> that we ſhould ſerue him in holines &amp; righteouſnes for euer. He hath giuen vs heauenlye graces many,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.10</note> and endued vs with his holye ſpirit, therefore muſt the bodie dye to ſinne,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.13. &amp; 4.24, 30. Rom. 8.10. 1. Pet. 1.15</note> &amp; the ſpirite liue for righteouſnes ſake. He is holye who hath called vs, therfore muſt we be holy in al our conuerſation. Let vs therefore (deare brethren) ſhew forth our obedience in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life,<note place="margin">Rom. 6. tot 2. pet. 1.10</note> and make ſtrong our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and calling by our good
<pb facs="tcp:3150:23"/> workes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.58.</note> and our labour ſhal not be in vaine in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Wee make great boaſtes and crakes, that wee be Chriſtians, let the ſame be proued true or falſe by our liues: for not euery one, that ſayth, Lord, Lorde,<note place="margin">Mat 7.21. &amp; 12.50.</note> ſhall enter into the kingdom of heauen, but he that doth the will of God: neither is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one brother or ſiſter to Chriſt, but onely thoſe which heare and keepe his word. &amp; this is the fruite of our obedience and righteouſnes towardes God.</p>
            <p>If we couet to be bleſſed and haue good ſucceſſe,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 1.8. 1. king. 2.3</note> we muſt needs beginne at this obedience of our faith.<note place="margin">Leuit. 26.3 12. Iere. 7.23.</note> Yf we will haue the Lord to be our God, and wee our ſelues to be his people, then muſt we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues to obey his word. yf we wil be counted the friendes of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.14.</note> then muſt we do whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he hath comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vs. Yf we
<pb facs="tcp:3150:24"/> will bee purified by faith in heart,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.22 Acts 15.9.</note> we muſt begin to obey the trueth. Yf we wil be ſafely armed againſt ſpiritual wickednes,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.17.</note> we muſt hold faſt the word of God. finally if we couet to be ſaued,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> we may not bee aſhamed of the Goſpell, but in all meeknes receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note> for it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſaue our ſoules. We ſay with the Iſraelites to Moſes,<note place="margin">Deut. 5.27 29.</note> that wee will obſerue the law. But, oh, that there were ſuch an heart in vs, to feare the Lorde, and to keepe his commandementes alway, that it might go well with vs, and with our children for euer. Wherefore as obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is better then ſacrifice,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.22. Deut. 4.6.</note> ſo let this be our wiſdome, with Noe to declare and ſhew forth our faith by our obedience vnto the word of God.</p>
            <p>Beſides al this, the obedience of righteous Noe, more plainely did appeare in that he did not folowe
<pb facs="tcp:3150:24"/> his owne purpoſe and deuiſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.15, 16.</note> but the appointment of God in this making of the arke. for he made it in length, in breadth, and height, &amp; in all other partes accordinglye as he was commanded. This is the wiſedome of God, who will not haue his Church builded accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to mannes deuiſe, but by the direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his worde.<note place="margin">Exo. 25.40 Act. 7.44. Ebr. 8.5.</note> When Moſes was commanded to build the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, he was ſtraightly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to do it according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paterne ſhewed vnto him in the mounte. When the Iſraelites were inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted how to ſerue God,<note place="margin">Deut. 12.29, 30, 31, 32.</note> when they came into the land of promiſe, they were forbidden to ſerue him after the maner of the Canaanites, and onely to worſhip him according to his lawe, without either turning to the right hand or to the left.<note place="margin">Ezra. 3.12, 13.</note> When the Iewes returned out of captiuitie, and repaired the ruines
<pb facs="tcp:3150:25"/> of the temple at Ieruſalem, they reedified it according to the former building made by Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſauiour Chriſt builded the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall arke &amp; temple of his church, he layed no other foundation but him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Ier. 3.11. eph. 2.10. mat. 16.18.</note> who was the rocke, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the which the gates of hel ſhould not preuaile. For finiſhing wherof, in the gathering together of the ſaintes,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20 rom. 15.18</note> he charged the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſtraitly, but to ſpeake, what he had taught them. This ought to be our ſpeciall care in building and reformation of religion, not to do what we thinke good, but as the Iſraelites before they tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in hand,<note place="margin">Exo. 28.30 nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 27.21 judg. 1.1.</note> aſked counſell of God: ſo muſt we in all our wayes be ruled by his word, which is the way for vs to walke in:<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.21.</note> which the holy ghoſt hath written,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.31.</note> that wee might beleue, &amp; in beleeuing might haue life. Wherefore whoſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:3150:25"/> bringeth any other Goſpel, though it were an angell from heauen,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> let him be accurſed, neither let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him into our houſes,<note place="margin">2. Ioh. 10.</note> neither bid him, God ſpeed. Now then, if this be the wiſedom of God, which Noe folowed, when he would not build, but as he was appointed, which Moſes, the Iewes, our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt and the apoſtles haue obſerued, what kinde of building may that be, which ſtandeth onely vpon mens deuiſes &amp; vaine imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, ſuch as is the whole reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Antichriſt? Surelye, it is like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion of the falſe prophets which ſewed pillowes vnder the elbowes of the Iewes, in flattring them in their ſinnes,<note place="margin">Ezek. 13.10, 15.</note> whileſt they dawbed &amp; walled their building with vntempered morter. Or it is like the houſe builded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſand,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.26</note> which becauſe of the weake fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can not well endure. Or it is
<pb facs="tcp:3150:26"/> like the ſtraw and ſtubble,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.12, 13.</note> which is laid vpon the good fundation, which at the fierie triall of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God conſumeth, and comes to nought: &amp; like as a paper arke or ſhip of leaues had bene a vaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe againſt the water to ſaue Noe and his familie: ſo is the whole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Antichriſt in vaine to ſaue our ſoules. What a fooliſh paradiſe delight they in, which make their arke or ſhip, of the rotten boardes of mannes traditions,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.8, 9.</note> which can neuer hold together? howe loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome an enſigne hath that veſſel,<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.17.</note> which caryeth the marke and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the beaſt? How lightlie, how perilouſly,<note place="margin">Iſai. 55.2.</note> &amp; howe vainely is he fraughted, that makes the chaff of bulles and pardons, his ſureſt traffique? What looſe anchre hold hath he,<note place="margin">Iſai. 64.6. luk. 17.10.</note> trow ye, that reſts &amp; rides vpon his owne merits and ſinfull workes? Howe vncertaine is his
<pb facs="tcp:3150:26"/> courſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.6. col. 2.18.</note> who directeth his race to ſaile to heauen by the mediation of ſaintes? What a cowardly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryner is he, that alwayes is afraid at the paper rockes and painted fyers of purgatorie? What vaine ordinance is holy bread,<note place="margin">2. The. 2.10 1, tim. 4.1. 2. tim. 4.3. 2 pet. 2.1, 2 apoc. 18.3, 4.</note> and holye water, to fight againſt the powers of hell? What foode or nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t can his beades, his palmes, his ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, his oyle, his aſhes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reliques, miniſter vnto him? What an vncertaine trumpet is ſounded,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> where the vanitie of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes is good ſeruice? finally, how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he euer ſaile in ſafety, who hath none ſitting at the ſtearne, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Antichriſt, whoſe purpoſe is to ouerthrowe the ſhip? In ſuch a naughtie arke and ſhip they ſaile, that row on forward without let, in their owne inuentions and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhip of papiſme and Idolatrie. but the arke &amp; ſhip of God, is made
<pb facs="tcp:3150:27"/> of the pyne trees of his word,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.12 ioh. 10.27. &amp; 17.3. Col. 1.14. Ephe. 4.30 Apoc. 7.3, 14. Mat. 11.28 Ebr. 4.14, 16. Mat. 16.18</note> pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched within &amp; without, with the aſſured grace of Chriſt, marked with the ſpirit of God and faith, fraughted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weighty merits of Chriſts paſſion, caſting ſure an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor in his promiſes directed by his mediation to the father, embolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his blood againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rocks and gates of death, defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinance of Chriſtian armour againſt the force of Sathan,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.11 1. theſ. 5.8.</note> and nouriſhed with the woorde and foode of life. Let vs no more then ſayle with them,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.4</note> nor yet retaine any of their abominations. But let vs addreſſe and prepare our ſelues with Noe to bee warned, let vs with readineſſe of fayth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, and let our good life expreſſe the ſame, in furthering the buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Church in our ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall callings, in all thinges being gouerned by the woorde of God,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:27"/> and then with <hi>Noe</hi> we be wel ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed. And thus much of the former part, whence it came that <hi>Noe</hi> was mooued to make the Arke.<note place="margin">2, Tim. 2.7.</note> The Lorde giue you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in all things, and he that hath eares to heare, let him heare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee prepared the Arke to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his houſholde.</hi> The Lorde (welbeloued) hath diuers means to ſaue his people from deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and therefore the Arke is ſaid firſt to haue had this effect, that Noe his family might bee ſaued thereby. For like as in the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Sodome, the litle towne <hi>Zoar</hi> was a refuge for the ſafetie of <hi>Lot,</hi> and his two daughters,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.20</note> &amp; <hi>Chaldea</hi> for Gods people, in the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iewrie, and <hi>Aegypt</hi> for <hi>Ioſeph, Marie</hi> &amp; the childe <hi>Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 2.13.</note> againſt the furious aſſaultes of <hi>Herode:</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the Arke was now
<pb facs="tcp:3150:28"/> the means which God would vſe for Noe his refuge, to ſaue him &amp; his fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drowning. This is the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing care which God hath ouer his people,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.15 &amp; 95.1. &amp;c</note> in defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadow of his wings, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling with the wicked. Let vs then caſt our care vpon him,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.7.</note> for he is carefull for vs: and then in the periſhing of the wicked, wee ſhall be ſafe within the Arke.</p>
            <p>Neyther muſt we thinke that the Arke was able to haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued Noe and his family from drowning: No no, it was the grace of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.8.</note> who had receiued him into fauour, which grace hee did aſſure him of, by preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him aliue within the Arke. Which thing the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> doth declare,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21</note> where he compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Baptiſme and the Arke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for like as in Baptiſme, not the putting away of the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines
<pb facs="tcp:3150:28"/> of the fleſh ſaueth vs, but a good conſcience, that maketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to God, by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt: euen ſo, not the outward making of the Arke, but fayth, beleeuing the promiſe of God vnto ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, iuſtified &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued Noe, whereof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arke was a holy ſigne or ſacrament, for the confirmation thereof: wherby we muſt obſerue, not to giue that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sacramentes, which is proper to the grace ſignified ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. For Sacraments,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 4. tot. Ioh. 1.33. 1. Cor. 10.5</note> neyther of them ſelues, nor in them ſelues, include the grace of God: for that belongeth to the Creator, and not vnto the creature. But they be as inſtruments, ſeales,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.10 exo. 12.11. mat. 26.26. &amp; 28.19.</note> pledges and confirmations of Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whereby he doth make more ſtrong his graces in our hearts, the fruits whereof we do receiue by a liuely fayth. For the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:3150:29"/> of Gods choſen reſteth not in ſacramentall ſignes,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.5.</note> but in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and good pleaſure of God.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom the promiſe was made,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.6. Rom. 4.3, 4</note> was iuſtified in belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the woorde of grace, long time before he receiued the ſigne or Sacrament of Circumciſion, which afterward was added for the confirmation of the promiſe. <hi>Iacob</hi> was choſen,<note place="margin">Gen. 25.23 Rom 9.11, 12. Act. 10.44, 47.</note> when he was yet vnborne, &amp; neuer had hearde of any Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie, beleeuing the words of <hi>Peter,</hi> were endued with the holy ghoſt, bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. Whereby wee learne that our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſteth not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Elementes, but in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Gods free mercie &amp; grace in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.4, 5</note> who before the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the worlde were layed, choſe vs by him to bee adopted vnto ſaluation, which grace hee
<pb facs="tcp:3150:29"/> ſealeth in our hearts by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, for our more behoofe, the vertue whereof we do receiue by fayth.</p>
            <p>Neyther herein muſt wee (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) abbridge or extenuate the dignitie of the Sacraments, and thinke they be but onely ſignes of grace, (as the papiſts falſely ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs) But as we ſaye not with the Iewes, nor with the papiſts,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 4. Conc. tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. ſeſ. 6. cap. 8.</note> that the Sacramentes doe giue grace, and ſo with them commit Idolatrie: ſo doe wee not ſaye that they are onely bare ſignes vnto the godlies fayth, but right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hold the meane betweene them both, &amp; belieue aſſuredly, with the ſacramentall ſigne,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.5. Mat. 26.26.</note> that grace is preſent vndoubtedly to the faith of him, that doth receiue the ſame aright. And thus ye ſee, that not the Arke, but the grace of God preſerued Noe and his familie,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:30"/> for whoſe ſaluation and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, the Arke was made an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument and meanes.</p>
            <p>It is not without good conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that the Arke was for the ſafetie of <hi>Noe</hi> his houſholde: for it doth expreſſe the right go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of his well diſpoſed family, wherein the feare of God did floriſh and continue. For like as when the head is wel &amp; ſound, and alſo the ſtomacke pure from hurtfull humours, the bodie is commonly well affected: euen ſo where the head or chief of any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is founde in fayth and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth God, it commonly goeth wel with all the houſholde. For this cauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> gaue commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto the Iewes,<note place="margin">Deu. 6.5, 6 7. &amp; 31.12.</note> that the law might be kept in their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, that they might proſper in all that they went about.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.11.</note> When <hi>Obed-edom</hi> had receiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arke
<pb facs="tcp:3150:30"/> of God into his houſe, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Lorde bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him and all his houſholde. When the widowe of <hi>Zarephath</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Eliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 17.10. &amp;c.</note> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther widowe of Iſrael in the dayes of <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 4.1 &amp;c.</note> had receiued the Prophets of God into their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, how mightily and merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lorde prouided for them, who is ignorant? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt had reſtored the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſonne to his health,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.53.</note> the ruler beleeued and all his family. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Zacheus</hi> had receiued Chriſt into his houſe,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.9.</note> and was conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſaluation came to the ſame houſhold. To be ſhort,<note place="margin">Act. 10.44.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> the Centurion embraced the Goſpel, his family alſo belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and was baptized, and the holy Ghoſt fell vpon them all which heard the preaching. How well that houſe was ordered,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:31"/> where <hi>Timothie</hi> was broght vp,<note place="margin">2. Tim, 1.5. &amp; 3.25.</note> his knowledge in the ſcriptures from a childe can witnes. This is the care of religion, which ought to bee kept in our houſes, and this is the good conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Lord looketh for at the handes of the houſholders of al degrees,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.1. &amp;c.</note> eſpecially if they looke for the bleſſing of God to fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, &amp; to be ſaued with Noe in the Arke of Chriſtes Church. But looke rounde about vs, and what ſhall we finde in our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? Is it not verified of vs, which the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpake ſo long agone vpon the Iewes: The children gather ſtickes,<note place="margin">Iere. 7.18.</note> the fathers make the fire, &amp; the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bake cakes for the queene of heauen? So fowly are our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies for the moſt part corrupted, with ignorance and ſuperſtition. In ſtead of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of God,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:31"/> and true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there is nothing to be found, but Atheiſme &amp; groſſe idolatrie. In ſteade of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and feare of Gods maieſtie, blaſpheming of his name,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.3.</note> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye other woorde moſt horribly powdered with an oth. In ſtead of honeſt and ſober liuing,<note place="margin">Ro. 13.13.</note> cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering and wantonnes, banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and minſtrilſie,<note place="margin">Iſa. 22.13.</note> eating and drinking like Epicures, for to morowe wee ſhall dye, thus fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our ſelues as an Oxe vnto the ſlaughter. In ſteade of godly meditations, abominable ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, as carding, dycing, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming of the giftes of God,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.1.</note> not lent to vs for ſuch a purpoſe. In ſteade of reading and hearing of the word of God,<note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> to comfort and exhort one another, the reading and good liking of prophane fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and fruitleſſe bookes, more meete for Mearcers ſhoppes, to wrappe
<pb facs="tcp:3150:32"/> their ſpices in, then for a wel diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed family to be taught &amp; nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured by. O where ſhall we finde a good Noe, to order his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde aright in feare and true o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and to forewarne them of the flood of euill to come? If to gouerne a family aright, were to purchaſe land, or for a man to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riche him ſelfe, or leaue a welthie ſonne, fewe were behinde with this endeuour. But O vaine ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haſt thou more deſire to leaue thy ſonne a fayre buylding, and ful of lands, then for to inſtruct him in the way of godlineſſe, and leaue him a vertuous conſcience? Haſt thou rather a deſire to hoorde vp treaſure for him,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.19.</note> with ruſt and mothe to be conſumed, then for to teach him the knowledge of God, which will not canker but laſt for aye?<note place="margin">Deut. 6.5. &amp; 28.2.</note> If eyther thou or thine will proſper well, you muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne
<pb facs="tcp:3150:32"/> in true religion to ſerue the Lorde, and then you ſhall bee bleſſed. Wilt thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know how to order thy family? Nouriſhe none, keepe none, I ſaye, make much of none,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.4.</note> but ſuch as feare the Lord. The godly king <hi>Dauid</hi> deſcribing the gouernement of his wel diſpoſed family, ſpeaketh in this wiſe:<note place="margin">Pſal. 101. toto.</note> 
               <hi>I will</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>walke in the vprightneſſe of my heart, in the middeſt of my houſe. I will ſet no wicked thing before mine eies: I hate the worke of them that fall away, it ſhall not cleaue vnto mee. A fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde heart ſhall depart from me: I will knowe none euill. Him, that priuily ſlandereth his neighbour, wil I deſtroy. Him, that hath a proude looke and high heart, I cannot ſuffer. Mine eies ſhalbe vnto the faythful of the lande, that they may dwell with me: he that walketh in a perfite way, he ſhall ſerue me. There ſhall no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful
<pb facs="tcp:3150:33"/> perſon dwel within my houſe. He that telleth lyes, ſhal not remaine in my ſight. &amp;c.</hi> Wherein we may plainly ſee, the right paterne of a well diſpoſed familie. We read in the Eccleſiaſticall ſtories of the primitiue church,<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſt. lib. 1. ca. 11.</note> that when Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius the Emperour woulde take a tryal of his houſhould ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, he commaunded them to ſhew forth of what religion they were. And when the time was appoynted vnto them, either to ſacrifice vnto the Idols, and ſo to remaine his ſeruantes, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to confeſſe Chriſt, &amp; ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part away, (for thus he thought to trie them) when euery one had ſhewed what he was, all ſuch as were Idolaters, &amp; denied Chriſt, he baniſhed from his Court, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them neuer to be faithfull towards him, who were vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full towardes God: and contrary
<pb facs="tcp:3150:33"/> to their expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he made much of them that feared the Lord, and did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe his name. An apt way for our behoofe, to vaniſh ſinne &amp; ſuperſtition from our families, that when the ende ſhal come, we may be ſaued with Noe and his familie in the Arke.</p>
            <p>And where as the holy Ghoſt ſayeth, that the arke was for the ſauegard of Noe and his familie, it is to admoniſh vs alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without the church of Chriſt, prefigured by the arke. For as the branche can not beare fruite,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.4.</note> except it doo abide within the vine, for elſe it dieth and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth: and as the hande cut fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, can not liue, but waſteth and conſumeth for lack of life: no more can we, except we do abyde in Chriſt: he is the vine, we are the bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches. This made the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Dauid call vpon the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:34"/> to remember him with the fauor of his people,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.4.</note> &amp; to viſite him with his ſaluation. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prophets deſcribed the reſtauration of the Church in the later dayes,<note place="margin">Iſai. 37.32. ioel. 2.32.</note> they did not teache that euery man ſhould be ſaued by what religion ſo euer he reteined, but onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſaluation to ſuch as fled to mount Sion, and to Ieruſalem, therby vnderſtanding the church of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ezec. 13.9.</note> When Ezechiel denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the wrath of God againſt the falſe prophets, he tolde them that they ſhould not be in the aſſembly of the Lords people, neither ſhuld be written in the writing of the houſe of Iſrael, neither ſhuld en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the lande of Iſrael, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhoulde knowe that he was the Lord God. Here then (welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) it ſtandeth vs vpon, to trie whether we be within the arke of the church of Chriſt or not, for els
<pb facs="tcp:3150:34"/> we periſh. For as the light of the ſunne auayleth not him that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in a darke and cloſe dungeon, where is alwayes night and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer day: euen ſo the graces of god do nothing helpe thoſe that lie in darkenes, and ſhadow of death, vntill they haue acceſſe into the Church of the faythfull. For ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as we be without the church and number of the faythfull, we are aliants, ſtrangers, pilgrims,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.19.</note> and men without God in this worlde: yea,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> wee bee enemies to God, vntil we be reconciled to the father by Chriſt.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.10 Ezec. 16.6.</note> We are without mercy, and polluted in our bloud, vntil by him we obtaine grace, &amp; be waſhed from our ſinnes.<note place="margin">Apoc. 1.5. Ephe. 2.1, 2. &amp;c.</note> We are dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, till we be raiſed vp with the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Apo. 14.8. &amp; 17.2. &amp; 18.3.</note> We be drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the poiſoned dregges of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, vntil we haue the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb facs="tcp:3150:35"/> triacle of Gods promiſes in the worde of the truth, for our preſeruation. How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought we, think you, to make haſte into this arke? your owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhal be my iudges. Surely, we can not be partakers of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.1. &amp;c.</note> except we be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the church of Chriſt: for onely vpon the ſame, they are beſtowed. Where can our ſoules be fed with the worde of God, but among the faythfull,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.27.</note> who are the ſheepe of Chriſt, &amp; heare his voice? Where ſhall we ſhew our thankfulneſſe, and confirme our faith with the ſacraments,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26. &amp; 28.19.</note> but in that Church, where thei be ſincerely miniſtred? Where can we haue forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.25. Eph. 2 8. Gal. 4.6. 1. Pet. 4.10</note> the grace of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and other his benefits, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we be within the Church, for whom he wrought the ſame? If
<pb facs="tcp:3150:35"/> therefore we hope for happines, &amp; looke aſſuredly for ſaluation, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt we keepe within the arke, &amp; then we ſhall be ſafe and ſounde. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be not deceyued with the title of the Church,<note place="margin">Iere. 7.4. &amp; 18.18. mat. 3.9.</note> which the aduerſaries always haue in their mouthes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath left vs his true and ſincere worde,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.27. Acts. 2.42. ephe. 5.25, 26, 27.</note> the right adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſacraments, and eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, to be the perfect marks of this his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall arke, whereto whileſt we do cleaue &amp; ſtick, we cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, or periſh with the wicked.</p>
            <p>What then (ſayth the papiſt) ſhall we thinke of all thoſe, which liued in the time of ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and were without the Church, which now we haue, which was ſo late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found? ſhall we iudge them to be damned? which thing we muſt needes do, except wee make the Church of Rome, the arke and
<pb facs="tcp:3150:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> Church of Chriſt. Concerning the Church of Rome, this is to be obſerued: that this Church of Rome which nowe is, is not the ſame, but only in place, with that which was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primitiue time. For then they followed the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Apoſtles, nowe they haue reuolted from the ſame, and Antichriſt ſitteth in the Temple of God.<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.4 apoc. 13.11. &amp;c.</note> And though the auncient fathers ſpeake much in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Rome, yet ſpeake they only of the church before that ſuperſtition crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame.</p>
            <p>And now before I anſwere to this queſtion, I muſt propounde the like to them. Before the time of Boniface the third, then Pope of Rome, when ſuperſtition and corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crept into the Church, and the light of the trueth began to be darkned, were all damned,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> which neuer before or after yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the ſea &amp; religion of Rome? Were all vndone which neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued tranſubſtantiation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius the third? or thoſe which neuer worſhipped their breaden god, which thing Honorius did decree? What need I ſpeake of other vanities? Were all the Prophetes and holy men of God, was Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and the auncient fathers of the primitiue Church, beſide the way, and out of the arke, which had the ſpirite of God,<note place="margin">Iſai. 59.21. iohn 16.13</note> to lead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into all truth, who taught the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred verities, and all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to ſaluation, and yet did neuer retaine ſuch vanities, as theſe men holde?<note place="margin">Matth. 24.2. theſ. 2.4. 1. tim 4.1. 2. pet. 2.1, 2</note> And if they did foretell any thing thereof, it was but to bid the Church beware of ſuch vngodlineſſe.</p>
            <p>And as for the arke or Church
<pb facs="tcp:3150:37"/> wherein we bee, it was before theirs was euer deuiſed, not new<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and of late yeeres, as many iudge, begunne, but renued and reformed of late, according to the worde of God, and is in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and doctrine, all one with the Church of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15. &amp; 22.18. deut. 18.18 ioh. 8.56. hebr. 13.8.</note> from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, directed by his ſpirit, and by the ſcepter of his worde. And albeit it was long hid through the tyrannie of the deuill, who draue the woman into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes,<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.8</note> yet ceaſed there not infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite numbers, to withſtande and gainſay the pollutions of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, whom God preſerued by his grace, though they could not bee ſeene by the eyes of men. For like as faith is chiefly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to God, and cannot be diſcerned by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſenſes, otherwiſe then by the declarations thereof:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19.</note> ſo the Lorde knewe onely who were
<pb facs="tcp:3150:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> his, whoſe fayth was knowne by their reſiſtance to the beaſt. When Iohn foretold the corruptions of the later times, and of the man of ſinne, he ſhewed that there was of all tribes many ſealed with the ſpirit of God,<note place="margin">Apoc. 7.4.</note> and marked with the blood of the Lambe, receyued by fayth, who periſhed not in the lake of Antichriſtes pollutions. He tolde that the two witneſſes of Chriſt (whereby he meant the ſmal number of the true Church)<note place="margin">Apoc. 11.3</note> ſhould be murthered by the beaſt:<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.7</note> who ſhould make warre with the ſaints of God, and torment them to death,<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.6</note> who ſhould be drunken with the blood of ſaints and holy martyrs, which could neuer haue beene, if there had bene none, to haue gainſaid his wicked ways. I neede not ſpeake of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Grecia, who ſtill with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popiſh vanities: yea there
<pb facs="tcp:3150:38"/> neuer ceaſed ſome, to withſtande hir erronious religion. Neither muſt we thinke that all was loſt, that liued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For why? the Lord hath wayes &amp; meanes vnknowen to man, to ſaue his people, as hee ſaued the thiefe,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.42</note> euen in the laſt houre,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> vpon the croſſe. And as he hath choſen in his ſecret purpoſe, vnknowne to man, who ſhall bee ſaued:<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.37. &amp; 10.28.</note> ſo will he not loſe one of them, but call them in due time.</p>
            <p>As for this argument, which they vſe herein,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.7, 8. iere. 9.14. ezek. 20 18.</note> it hath bene a ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke to the wicked of all ages. The Iewes were mooued with nothing ſo much, to gainſay the doctrine of the Prophets, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them from their Idolatrie, but that their fathers had liued, as they did at that preſent: and yet they ought not to haue folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their fathers further, then their fathers folowed the worde
<pb facs="tcp:3150:38"/> of trueth.<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.20, 22.</note> The woman of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria reaſoned thus againſt our Sauiour Chriſt: Our fathers (ſaith ſhee) worſhipped in this mountaine: but hee made hir an anſwere, that they worſhipped they knewe not what, for ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion came of the Iewes.</p>
            <p>But it is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth is opened, to leape from the ſame, into the ſeat of iudgement, and define who were ſaued, who were not: but rather referring al to the mercy and good pleaſure of God, both concerning our forefathers &amp; all others, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour our wittes to do his will. For now this thing is condemnation,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.19.</note> that light is come into the world, &amp; men loue darknes more then light. And to ſaye the trueth, if ſome of our elders in the times of ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, had had the trueth as wee haue no we reueyled, they would long
<pb facs="tcp:3150:39"/> ſince haue repented in ſackecloth &amp; aſhes.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.21</note> But it is greatly to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which our ſauiour Chriſt doth threaten to come to paſſe againſt the Iewes, to be layde againſt vs. For as the men of Niniue repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted at the preaching of Ionas,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.41</note> and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preaching of Chriſt, who was greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ionas: euen ſo the good and faithfull dealing which they had in times paſt in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cauſes, doth reprooue our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and tell what they would haue bin if they had had the light. And therefore a good father ſaieth full well:<note place="margin">Beza epiſ. 1.</note> Men had better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces then, and leſſe knowledge: now haue they more knowledge &amp; worſe conſciences.</p>
            <p>But if theſe men will bragge of auncientie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt they looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the olde wayes of the Prophets and Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Iere. 6.16.</note> &amp; to Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note> in whom are all the treaſures
<pb facs="tcp:3150:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> of wiſedome and vnderſtanding: for Antiquitie without veritie, is nothing worth. If they would boaſt of vnitie, the ſame muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in true doctrine,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3. phil. 2.2.</note> and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, &amp; not in ydle ceremonies. If they will glory of ſucceſſion, the ſame will helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing, except they follow the ancient fathers,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.1. phil. 3.17.</note> in ſinceritie of doctrine and godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation: for they be not the true ſucceſſours of holy men, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſit in their chayres, but they which folow their faith and godly workes.<note place="margin">Diſt. 40.</note> And if they make theyr vaunt of multitude, the moſt parte are not alwayes beſt inclined. For why? narowe is the way, that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto lyfe,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.13, 14.</note> and fewe there be that fynde it, but wyde is the way y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leadeth to perdition. And though many be called, yet fewe be choſen.<note place="margin">Mat. 22.14</note> Only Noe his familie which were but eight in all, were ſaued aliue,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3150:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> when all the worlde beſides was drowned. And though they bragge much of the title of the church,<note place="margin">Iere. 7 4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> the church, yet haue they made thereof a denne of theeues,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.33 mar. 12.1.</note> &amp; broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe the vineyard of the Lorde, &amp; erred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the way of trueth. Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore repaire not vnto them, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arke of Chriſt, &amp; ſo wee ſhall be ſure and ſafe, from drowning &amp; deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it is to be noted, that notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding Noe and his familie were ſafe within the Arke, and ſure from drowning, yet were they toſſed to &amp; fro, with the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful waues &amp; ſourging ſeas, &amp; alſo diſmaid with the cloudy &amp; miſtie ayre, not much vnlike vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our Sauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.24. mar. 4.35.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeas at the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous tempeſtes, toſſing the ſhip where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were. But as then our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt moſt comfortably
<pb facs="tcp:3150:40"/> did awake, and commaunde both winds and ſeas to be ſtill: ſo was the merciful God careful for Noe in theſe afflictions within the Arke, and after many weariſome dayes, did bring him ſafe to land. Thus is the Church of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the raging tempeſtes and byllowes of this worlde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with many tribulations,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.33. act. 14.22. 2. tim. 3.12.</note> before ſhe can arriue to the hauen of heauenly happines. Albeit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham had the Lorde to bee his buckler and exceeding great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde,<note place="margin">Gen. 12. &amp; 20.</note> vnder whoſe defence hee was ſafely garded, yet was hee tryed by famine and other daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers many, for the better exerciſe of his faith.<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.1. &amp; 66.12.</note> The Prophet Dauid was well aſſured of the Lordes fauour and mightie protection, that hee needed not to feare, yet was his fayth and patience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by many afflictions, both of
<pb facs="tcp:3150:41"/> wicked Saul and others mo, and him ſelfe ordayned to go through fire and water, before he came to the place of ſweet refreſhing. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour and captaine Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.21</note> the head of the Church did with our fleſhe aſcende into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, hee paſſed through the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous torments of the croſſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaintes and holy men of God attained euerlaſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, their fayth &amp; patience was tryed by the manifolde perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Antichriſt and his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.12 Apoc. 11.7. &amp; 12.11. &amp; 14.12.</note> And euen in theſe dayes, the beaſt and man of ſinne, and ſonne of perdition, together with many kings and nobles of the earth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.2. Apoc. 17.12, 13.</note> doth breathe grieuous threates and wicked counſell againſt the Church and ſpouſe of Chriſt, and ſtirre vp ſtrife all the day long, wherein we muſt learne (dearely beloued) to arme our ſelues with
<pb facs="tcp:3150:41"/> fayth and patience againſt ſuch perſecutions. For although wee be within the Arke, yet will the waters of afflictions ſtreame and ſtriue againſt vs.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.24.</note> Though our fayth bee buylded vpon the rocke and ſure fundation Chriſt Ieſus, yet will the boyſterous blaſtes and windes of wickednes aſſault &amp; ſhake vs, if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make vs fall. Wee muſt needs be like faſhioned to our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and captaine Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29. 2. Tim. 2.11.12.</note> to ſuffer with him, that wee may raigne with him, to dye with him, that we may riſe againe with him,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.5, 7.</note> to be partakers of his ſorowes, that we may be fellowes at his ioyes. Wee muſt needes be tryed as fine golde from baſe mettall,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.7. &amp; 4.12, 13, 14. Ebr. 12.7. &amp;c.</note> as the godly from the vngodly, and as children from baſtardes in the fierie fornace of afflictions. Wee muſt needes haue the reliques of
<pb facs="tcp:3150:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſinne puniſhed in vs, and therfore wee are toſſed within the Arke &amp; chaſtiſed of the Lorde,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.32.</note> leaſt with the wicked worlde we ſhould be condemned. Hereby the Lord wil alſo haue vs to bee ſtirred vp, to ſeeke for ſuccour from his throne of grace in calling vpon him in the day of trouble.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> Our fayth, our patience and other vertues moe, muſt needs be explored &amp; known.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.7. iam. 1.3, 4, 12. 2. Cor. 5.1, 2.</note> we muſt be inflamed with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the life immortall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we ſhalbe crowned, after we haue endured tentation. Neither muſt we in the middeſt of theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions be diſcomfited or faynt-hearted: for why? wee abide no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but it is according to the will of God,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.17 Mat. 5.11, 12.1. pet. 2.21.</note> neyther happeneth any thing vnto vs, but the ſame hath happened to the godly of all ages. And although for a time we cate the breade of teares, and
<pb facs="tcp:3150:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> drinke the waters of aduerſitie, yet afterwarde ſhall we be filled with the heauenly Manna,<note place="margin">Apoc. 2.17 &amp; 22.17. Pſal. 30.5.</note> &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of euerlaſting life. Heauines may well endure for a night, but ioye commeth in the morning. The Lorde hath promiſed to bee preſent with vs, by his grace,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.10 1. pet. 4.14 &amp; 2. pet. 2.9</note> and to comfort vs in diſtreſſe, and to deliuer vs out of tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And though wee bee toſſed in the Arke for a yere, perhappes for more, yet ſhall wee reſt at length vpon Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia,<note place="margin">Gen. 8.4, 5</note> and the floodes bee dryed vp: and then the Lorde ſhall take vengeance of them who here af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and moleſt vs.<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.20.</note> And in the meane time, he ſhall turne their hearts that they do vs no wrong, as hee turned the heart of Eſau towardes Iacob.<note place="margin">Gen. 33.4.</note> Hee ſhall call them backe from perſecuting vs, as hee called Saul from folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and purſuing after Dauid,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 23.27</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3150:43"/> yea hee ſhall put ſuch a ſnaffle in their mouthes, then they ſhall doe no more then in his ſecrete proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he hath appoynted.<note place="margin">Act. 2.23. &amp; 4.28.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.12.</note> when we be impugned by ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and the ſpirituall powers of wickedneſſe aboue our bodily reache, when wee walke through the middeſt of many falſe brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.26.</note> and by theſe aduerſaries of the trueth be reproched, ſlandered, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled and perſecuted, &amp; alſo wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened through our owne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, let this bee our hope and comfort, that wee bee within the Arke, and once the ioyful day wil come,<note place="margin">Iſai. 25.8. apoc. 7.17</note> when God ſhall wipe away all ſorowes from our eyes, and crowne vs with glory and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And therefore, whileſt we be within the Arke, let vs not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire for trouble and aduerſitie, for God is faythfull who hath promiſed.<note place="margin">Ebr. 10.23.</note> And thus much of the
<pb facs="tcp:3150:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> firſt effect of the Arke.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde effect it had, was touching the wicked, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>Whereby he condemned the worlde.</hi> Whileſt Noe and his family (dearely beloued) were lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g exerciſed in the making of the Arke, and thereby obeyed the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God, they did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the ſtubbernes of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked which refuſed to do the ſame, and to be warned, and ſo tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way al excuſes from them, ſo that as the Arke was for the ſafetie of Noe, ſo was it likewiſe a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for the wicked. This is (deare brethren) the nature of the admonitions and warnings of God, which for the moſt part haue a double effect, for to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which beleeue the ſame, they are the ſauour of life, to life,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.16</note> but to the wicked which refuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, they are the taſte of death vnto
<pb facs="tcp:3150:44"/> deſtruction.<note place="margin">Exo. 14.</note> For as the redde ſea was a ſafe paſſage for the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites comming out of Egypt, and a drowning to the Egyptians: And as the fire of Babylon hurt not the three childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caſt into the Ouen,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.21, 25.</note> but yet burnt the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which caſt them in: And as the Lyons ſaued Daniel aliue,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.22, 24.</note> but quickly did deuoure his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers: euen ſo is the nature of the word of God. Wherefore it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the fire, which melteth waxe, and hardeneth clay, and to the trumpe in battell,<note place="margin">Iere. 6.17.</note> which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth ſome, &amp; diſcourageth other ſome. And as the rayn com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen returneth not thither againe,<note place="margin">Iſai. 55.10.</note> but maketh the earth fruitfull: euen ſo ſhall the woorde of God accompliſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where, whatſoeuer his will is. And therefore as it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to the wicked, ſo is it
<pb facs="tcp:3150:44"/> the power of God vnto ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> to all thoſe which beleeue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Let vs therfore ſubmit our ſelues &amp; all our cogitations to the ſame,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.5.</note> leaſt in refuſing it, we be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby, and all excuſe taken from vs.</p>
            <p>But it fareth with this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, whereof fewe embrace the trueth and liue therafter, as it did with the worlde in the dayes of Noe. For as then they were diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to Noe,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 6. 1. pet. 3 20 &amp; 2. pet. 2.5</note> and contemned the preaching of righteouſnes: ſo nowe many good Noes preache the woorde ſincerely, but alas, it falleth into the heartes of many,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.3, 4.</note> but as good ſeed into euill grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and therefore, eyther bringeth forth litle, or els no fruite at al: the contempt whereof was then, and ſo is nowe, the cauſe of manye plagues.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> What baniſhed Adam out of Paradiſe, &amp; brought ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:3150:45"/> woes vpon him &amp; all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note> but the contempt of Gods worde? what ouerthrewe the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites in the wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.9. ebr. 3.12. &amp;c. Iude. 5. &amp;c.</note> &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued their poſteritie in the lande of Canaan ſo often, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt hereof? what loſt Saul the fauour of God and the ſcepter of his kingdome,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 15.</note> or what led Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael and Iuda into captiuitie,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 17.14. iere. 9.12, 13. luk. 14.18. rom 11.21. ebr. 4.1.</note> but the contempt of this? what helde the Iewes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſupper &amp; graces of God? what depriued them of the dignitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; benefite of the kingdome, but the contempt of this? what ſhould I ſpeake of the manifolde plagues of God powred vpon this realme of England, &amp; nations rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs for the contempt of his worde? And then how happeneth it,<note place="margin">Nom. 11.5, 6, 7.</note> that we ſtill loath the ſame, as the Iſraelites did Manna in the wildernes? or is it that we would
<pb facs="tcp:3150:45"/> be in the ſpiritual Egypt of filthie papiſtrie againe, and ſo depriue our ſelues of the land of reſt?</p>
            <p>But as in Noe his time,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.12.</note> all fleſhe, euen all degrees were ſore corrupted: ſo is it nowe, moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable to beholde, all fleſhe is gone aſtray, and iniquitie ripe on euery ſide. Looke into the heads &amp; high eſtates of al ſorts, who ſhuld haue knowledge &amp; bee lightes for others: &amp; euen theſe (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith) haue broken the yoke &amp; burſt the bonds aſunder.<note place="margin">Iere. 5.5.</note> Where ſhould be zeale and true religion? Where ſhoulde be godlineſſe and innocencie of life, but chiefly in theſe? but doe we not ſee many of them, eyther profeſſed papiſtes, or manifeſt diſſemblers? Where ſhould the miniſterie be relieued and vpholde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by theſe? and do not diuers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them make ſpoyle &amp; hauocke of the Church goodes, to
<pb facs="tcp:3150:46"/> cloath and feede them ſelues, and ſtarue the poore? Where ſhoulde the good and godly lawes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande be better executed, but by theſe? They doe not make, they marre and breake the lawes. And if there bee ſome godly ſtatutes made,<note place="margin">Iſocrates <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it is to true in ſome, which the Oratour ſayth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Manie lawes we make, but wee litle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard or keepe them. And as the Poet ſaith, <hi>Auro venalia iura.</hi> Why are the lawes like ſpyders webs, to let the waſpe eſcape and to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the flye? If gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offend, as their hands are ryfeſt in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,<note place="margin">Ezra. 9.2.</note> they haue their purſe, &amp; courtly friendes, they ſhall eſcape vnpuniſhed: But aye the poore goes by the walles. What els is this, but euen to make and ſel the lawes? I neede not ſpeake of bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and inſatiable officers, who
<pb facs="tcp:3150:46"/> rather ſeeke for gaine, then for maintaining of the trueth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.4.</note> who make the poore their praye and ſpoyle. But this I ſaye, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an ancient king hath ſaid: <hi>Saepè boni iudices habent malos vicarios,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Foxus. to 1. pag. 111.</note> 
               <hi>quorum reatibus ipſi domini conſtringuntur, ſi non eos coër<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceant, &amp; à rapacitate cohibeant.</hi> that is, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes good magiſtrates haue euill vicegerentes, or vnder offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, with whoſe offences the heades them ſelues are chayned, if they ſtay them not, and refraine them from greedines. And what may we rightly iudge to bee the cauſe of theſe offences, but euen the neglect of the woorde of God, which ſhould teache vs to doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and to flee from euill?</p>
            <p>And as the contempt in this degree is horrible, ſo woulde I wiſhe it ſpreade no further: then ſhould our miniſterie be the freer from offence, and our goſpel haue the better ſpeede. But it is herein,
<pb facs="tcp:3150:47"/> as Ieremie ſaid,<note place="margin">Iere. 2.8.</note> The prieſts ſay not, Where is the Lord? and they that ſhould miniſter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, know not the Lorde: the paſtours haue offended againſt him, &amp; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets propheſie in Baal, and goe after things which do not profit. Our miniſterie is fowly (to ſaye the trueth) corrupted: for whileſt ignorant miniſters and dombe dogges,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 12.31. 2. chro. 13.9. iſa. 56 10.</note> more like to Ieroboams prieſts, and ſacrificing maſſemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, haue cure &amp; charge of ſoule, while tagge &amp; ragge may bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to this function, whileſt gentlemen may haue the profits of the flocke, and hire Sir Iohn Lackelatine to ſing or ſay the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, howe ſhall the Goſpell haue good ſucceſſe? whileſt Church to Church is ioyned,<note place="margin">Act. 20.28. nehe. 6.3.</note> and non reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies borne withall and well liked, what can go forewarde in the building of the Lorde? where
<pb facs="tcp:3150:47"/> preaching is but once a quarter (I ſay not where it is ſeldome or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, which I might) or once a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth (which ſome thinke more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> needes, &amp; if it be eche Saboth, it is counted a worke of ſupereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) how can the people be reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from their vanities, or kept within the fold in dew obedience? Go to, what ſpringes of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in theſe eſtates? euen effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all ryot, and running into ſinne, of the inferiour ſort. For as the wall within and eke without, is made of ſquared ſtones, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the which the leſſe ſtones are contained, to make the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the miniſter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Churche, &amp; the Magiſtrate in the common weale, ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and vpholde the meaner ſort in dewe obedience. If then the ſquared ſtones within, or els with out fall downe, the leſſe can neuer
<pb facs="tcp:3150:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> long endure, becauſe they lacke their ſtay. And of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt in theſe degrees, it comes to paſſe, that lacke of diſcipline &amp; good liuing is the cauſe of many ſinnes,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.17.</note> both in the Church and commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale. Neither woulde I haue this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, that whileſt eccleſiaſticall officers may for money diſpenſe with offendours,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 15.8. 1. kin. 20.42.</note> and alſo vayne pitie in the common weale maye ſhadowe iniquities, the Churche can not go well. Surely, Surely it is with Englande, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Oſee ſaide it was with Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.1, 2, 3.</note> The Lord hath a controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with the people of the land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no mercy, no truth, no knowledge of God in the land. But by ſwearing, lying, killing, ſtealing and whoring men break out, and blood toucheth blood: therfore ſhal the land mourne, &amp;c. How ripe the ſinnes of England
<pb facs="tcp:3150:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> be for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſickle of Gods ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance,<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.15.</note> euerye Chriſtian eye can teſtifie. And yet for all this, we are faſt a ſleepe with the careleſſe world, in the time of Noe. We eat &amp; drinke,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.37 luk. 17.28. 1. pet. 3.20</note> we marie &amp; giue to mariage, moſt like, vntill the flood ſhall take vs hence:<note place="margin">Amos. 6.4.</note> wee lye vpon our ſoft cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and put away the euill day farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: we bleſſe our ſelues,<note place="margin">Deut. 29.19.</note> when wee heare the threatnings of the Lord and curſes of his law, and ſay, We ſhall feele none euill: we are drunken with fooliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 25.36</note> vntill Abigail bring vs word that we muſt dye. We ſpoyle, and make our ſelues merie with the goods of other men,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 30.16</note> as the Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites did in Ziklag, vntill Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Gods ſcourge come vpon vs to wounde vs to death and make a reſkewe.<note place="margin">Da. 5.3, 30.</note> We drinke with Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar in bowles, vntill the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des take away our kingdome. we
<pb facs="tcp:3150:49"/> enriche our ſelues,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.18.</note> &amp; alſo enlarge our barnes, and laye vp treaſure in ſtore for many yeres, and yet this preſent night our ſoule muſt be taken away,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note> and then who ſhal poſſeſſe our ſubſtance? we waſte and ſpoyle our maſters goodes,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.1.</note> &amp; liue vnmindfull of our duetie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we be called to render an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of our ſtewardſhippe. we ſleepe full harde with the fooliſh virgins,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.5.</note> and our lampes quite put out, till that the bridegrome be gone in, and the doore faſt loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked that we can not enter. We ſit like the proud ſtrumpet Babylon,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.7, 8.</note> &amp; feede our ſelues with folly, that we ſhall feele no ſorowe nor wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowhead, &amp; yet al ſorows ſhal ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly come vpon vs. Finally we ſay,<note place="margin">1. The. 5.3.</note> Peace, peace, &amp; all things qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, euen when the end is at hand. Nay rather,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.13</note> let vs watche &amp; pray, and haue our lampes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes
<pb facs="tcp:3150:49"/> burning, that we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into reſt with the bridegrome at his comming, &amp; leaue betimes our great ſecuritie, leaſt we periſh with the wicked.</p>
            <p>It is reported of Tamberlane the king of the Parthians, who tearmed himſelfe <hi>Iram dei &amp; orbis vaſtitatem,</hi> to haue ſet vp three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral dais three ſeueral kinds of tents, wherof the firſt was white, betokening mercie, if his enemies would y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> day yeeld: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d day, the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were red, betokeni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of the rulers, the thirde was black, ſignifying the burning and deſtruction of the citie, neyther was there hope of mercie when the white tents were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down, although they humbled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with lawrell. Let vs goe foorth with lawrell braunches in this our time and day of grace, for it is a fearefull thing to fall
<pb facs="tcp:3150:50"/> into the hands of the liuing God, who is a conſuming fire: let vs be admoniſhed by the woorde of trueth, or els the ſame will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs with the wicked.</p>
            <p>But the time is paſt, &amp; I haue wearied you to much, I wil ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore note one worde or two, of the laſt wordes, and ſo make an ende.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He was made the heire of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, which is according to fayth.</hi> This is nowe the acceptation &amp; reward of Noe his faith, who firſt was receiued into fauour by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing the promiſe of God, and thereby had God a mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this his obedience was accepted, not for anye the worthines of fleſh &amp; blood, which was none,<note place="margin">Ro. 8.33, 34.</note> but by the free grace of God, accepting in good worth, what he did. For when faith bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the promiſes of God concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſaluation,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15, 17.</note> &amp; apprehendeth
<pb facs="tcp:3150:50"/> the adoption of the children, then foloweth the inheritaunce of our righteouſneſſe, for that we being by fayth the children of God, are heires, euen felowe heires with Chriſt of his kingdome. For after we beleeue, we are ſealed with the ſpirit of promiſe, which is the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of our inheritance,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.13 14.</note> vntill the redemption of the poſſeſſion, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed vnto the praiſe of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. This is that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.7.</note> that wee being iuſtified by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God, ſhould be made heires, according to the hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life. And for this cauſe is Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mediatour of the newe Teſtament, that through death,<note place="margin">Ebr. 9.15.</note> which was for the redemption of the tranſgreſſions which were in the former Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they which were called, might receiue the promiſe of the eternal inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Bleſſed be God therefore, (let vs
<pb facs="tcp:3150:51"/> all ſay) euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.3.</note> which according to his aboundant mercie, hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten vs againe, vnto a liuely hope, by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt from the dead, to an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance immortal and vndefiled, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in heauen for vs.</p>
            <p>This inheritance of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.1. ebr. 11.8.</note> Abraham behelde with the eyes of fayth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he forſooke his owne countrey looking for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and euerlaſting in heauen, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing in ſpirite to ſee the day of Chriſt the Meſſias.<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.56.</note> This inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance Dauid longed after,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1. &amp; 27 13.</note> when like as the Harte deſired the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brookes, euen ſo his ſoule lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged after the Lorde, hoping to ſee the goodneſſe of the Lorde in the lande of the liuing. This inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance the Apoſtles beleeued to haue,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.68.</note> when they confeſſed Chriſt to bee the Sonne of God, and
<pb facs="tcp:3150:51"/> to haue the woordes of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. This inheritance the Saints in the reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caſt their eyes vpon,<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.11. &amp; 14.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when with patience they endured the tormentes of death, becauſe they woulde not yeelde to the pollutions of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. And this is that crowne of righteouſneſſe which wee deſire, whileſt wee dayly pray,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.2. Apoc. 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>Thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come.</hi> Come Lorde Ieſu, come quickly. Finally this is that inheritaunce of fayth, which our Sauiour Chriſt hath already ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken poſſeſſion of for vs, and which we ſhal feele, when he ſhal ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaye,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.34</note> Come ye bleſſed of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, poſſeſſe the kingdome prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you, from the beginning of the worlde.<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.48.</note> Then ſhall all ſorow and teares hee wiped from our eyes, then ſhal we ſee death, ſinne, Sathan, Antichriſt &amp; his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers trodden vnder foot,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.55, 56, 57.</note> and ſwalow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:3150:52"/> vp in victorie,<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.2</note> whileſt we ſhall ſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſongs of triumph before the throne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lamb, &amp; this ſhalbe the reward of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our faith. Wherefore whileſt we ſee the end to draw nere,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.7. &amp; 2. Pet. 3.11.</note> let vs prepare &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe our ſelues, that we may be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arke of Chriſts church, ſo ſhal we be ſure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtruction, &amp; aſſured of euerlaſting happines, to be the reward &amp; inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our faith, giuen vs of God for the loue &amp; worthines of his onely ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ro. 6.23.</note> our onely redeemer &amp; Sauiour: to whome with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Ghoſt three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct perſons, and one inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and euerlaſting God, be al honour, glory, praiſe and dominion for euer. So be it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Bleſſed are they vvhich heare the vvorde of God and keepe it. <bibl>Luk. 11.28.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3150:52"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes Maieſtie.</head>
            <p>ANNO. 1578.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  <head>TIGRE: REO. ANIMALE DEL. ADAM. VECCHIO. FIGLI VOLO. MERCE. LEVANGELIO. FATTO. N'ESTAT. AGNELLO</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
